<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>H.Gens</title><link href="https://h-gens.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://h-gens.github.io/feeds/outdoors.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://h-gens.github.io/</id><updated>2015-11-26T17:39:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Cycling across the U.S.</title><link href="https://h-gens.github.io/cycling-across-the-us.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-26T17:39:00+01:00</updated><author><name>H.G.</name></author><id>tag:h-gens.github.io,2015-11-26:cycling-across-the-us.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One year, I got it in my head that I wanted to ride across the country.  I was several years removed from being an active cyclist but was experienced enough so that the prospect of such an undertaking wasn't daunting.  My only concerns were weather, mechanical problems, and logistics (food/hotels/water).  What follows is a description of my approach in the event that someone else is searching for information on this topic.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Details&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My approach was atypical.  Most folks camp and generally take their time, so most everyone I met was surprised by how little I was carrying.  I came from a racing background (amateur level but way too into it) and preferred going fast and doing bigger distances.  To realize these preferences, I had to travel as lightly as possible and spend more money.  Being out of cycling shape coupled with the big distances led to some physical problems (noted below under &lt;strong&gt;Physical toll&lt;/strong&gt;).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose one could say that I traveled "ultralight," although I hesitate to use that term since I've read of riders carrying less.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="profile view of loaded bike" src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day37_IMGP0267.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Route&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started inland in VA and ended inland in CA.  I had enough cycling experience in both start/end locations and wasn't interested in the "dip your wheel in both oceans" thing.  Much more appealing was traveling through the middle of the U.S.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My route followed the &lt;a href="http://www.adventurecycling.org/routes-and-maps/adventure-cycling-route-network/transamerica-trail/"&gt;TransAmerica Trail&lt;/a&gt; to Pueblo, CO and then switched to the &lt;a href="http://www.adventurecycling.org/routes-and-maps/adventure-cycling-route-network/western-express/"&gt;Western Express&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;strong&gt;Highly recommended&lt;/strong&gt; maps are available from &lt;a href="http://www.adventurecycling.org/"&gt;Adventure Cycling&lt;/a&gt;.  These maps show what level of service is available in each town (hotel, gas station, etc.), which is incredibly useful.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total distance - 3200 miles&lt;br /&gt;
Number of riding days - 30&lt;br /&gt;
Number of rest days - 5&lt;br /&gt;
Daily average excluding rest days - 105&lt;br /&gt;
Minimum daily distance - 45 miles&lt;br /&gt;
Maximum daily distance - 180 miles  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Weather and timing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timing is important since some of the mountain passes along the route can be closed due to snow.  The year I left was a heavy snowfall year and some passes had stayed closed into June.  I saw heavy amounts of snow on both sides of the road in early July when crossing into CA.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what direction you ride, the wind can be against you for days on end in the western, more open portion of the route.  Prevailing winds (aka &lt;a href="https://suite.io/jon-plotkin/5xp02e9"&gt;westerlies&lt;/a&gt; in the U.S.) are directed from west to east, so conventional wisdom says to start in the west.  A rider who had done the route before told me of fighting the wind for days on the Western Express while heading &lt;strong&gt;east&lt;/strong&gt;, which just emphasizes how locally variable the weather can be.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving to the Western Express portion of the route late in the year can also be problematic due to increased temperatures.  Furthermore, too late in the year and there can be flooding when rainstorms occur.  &lt;a href="http://www.adventurecycling.org/"&gt;Adventure Cycling&lt;/a&gt; suggests finishing the Western Express portion by July.  Also, there can be flooding in the midwest approaching the Mississippi depending on the time of year.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tornados are a potential reality in some portions of the route.  I checked the weather pretty carefully every day but there's not much to do (other than lay in a ditch?) if you are caught without shelter nearby.  I took refuge in a church during a bad thunderstorm in KY that had at least one local heading to a friend's basement (the late-morning sky turned a strange brown color).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mountain passes and parts of the western states can be incredibly cold, even in late June.  I had trouble descending Monarch pass in CO because of cold hands and experienced an unbelievably cold morning in Utah that had me dismount and shiver until the sun got higher.  It's something I just accepted since the goal was to travel light.  Thankfully, cold weather wasn't a problem outside those two instances.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left in late May and arrived early July.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Budget&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I credit card camped (i.e., stayed in hotels) and ate in restaurants for dinner, which drove the budget up.  Relying on hotels heavily influenced how far I could ride in a day since there had to be a hotel where I finished.  Dinner was often expensive because I would order the same thing twice.  Away from big cities, hotels averaged significantly less.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large portion of my budget went to gear.  I had wheels custom built with a high spoke count to avoid a serious mechanical issue in the middle of nowhere.  If your rim cracks or the wheel otherwise fails you can be stuck in a town with no bike shop waiting for a shipment to arrive.  There aren't a lot of bike shops directly along the route.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gear&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following amount of items in a saddlebag on a smaller bike may be cumbersome (I had a 65cm frame).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bicycle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- 2004 Cannondale R2000 with Ultegra group&lt;br /&gt;
- custom made 700C wheels using DT Swiss parts&lt;br /&gt;
- &lt;a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=store.catalog&amp;amp;CategoryID=4&amp;amp;ProductID=1"&gt;Revelate Viscacha saddlebag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- SKS Raceblade front/rear fenders with added 3M reflective tape&lt;br /&gt;
- small saddle bag that one might normally have on a road bike&lt;br /&gt;
- Specialized Roubaix Armadillo tires, 700x23/25c&lt;br /&gt;
- Speedplay X2 pedals  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- allen wrenches&lt;br /&gt;
- big frame pump (to reach 100+ psi)&lt;br /&gt;
- chain lube&lt;br /&gt;
- chain tool (full size because I hate miniature ones)&lt;br /&gt;
- leatherman&lt;br /&gt;
- new chain and rear cassette halfway through&lt;br /&gt;
- Park Tools tire boots (instead of a spare tire)&lt;br /&gt;
- Schraeder to Presta adapter&lt;br /&gt;
- spare spokes taped to frame&lt;br /&gt;
- spare SRAM chain masterlink&lt;br /&gt;
- tire levers, patch kit, two spare tubes  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clothes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- arm warmers&lt;br /&gt;
- Keen closed-toe sandals&lt;br /&gt;
- one pair of shorts&lt;br /&gt;
- two cycling jerseys&lt;br /&gt;
- two pairs of cycling shorts&lt;br /&gt;
- two pairs of socks&lt;br /&gt;
- two pairs of underwear&lt;br /&gt;
- two small Sea-to-Summit dry bags&lt;br /&gt;
- two t-shirts&lt;br /&gt;
- windproof vest  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electronics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- camera/phone&lt;br /&gt;
- flashing red LED rear light (always on, day or night)&lt;br /&gt;
- Garmin Oregon GPS&lt;br /&gt;
- handlebar light&lt;br /&gt;
- iPad&lt;br /&gt;
- rechargeable NiMH batteries and charger&lt;br /&gt;
- SPOT satellite tracker  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misc&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
- DZ Nutz chamois cream&lt;br /&gt;
- four water bottles&lt;br /&gt;
- hydration backpack purchased in KS&lt;br /&gt;
- small combination bike lock (I hardly used it)&lt;br /&gt;
- sunscreen&lt;br /&gt;
- toothbrush + small toothpaste tube  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stored the paper maps on the iPad by taking pictures of them.  I also manually created the entire route in the Garmin mapping software and saved it in the GPS.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All garments were made from wicking polyester.  Underwear/socks/shirts went into one of the drybags.  The other drybag contained electronics.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything fit into the giant saddlebag, which predictably swayed slightly when pedalling while standing up.  I got used to it.  Once the trip was over I had to relearn how to ride standing up since the swaying compensation had become innate.  The sandals were strapped to the saddlebag/saddle.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every night in the hotel room I would hand wash the cycling clothes I wore that day in the tub.  I used a washing machine a few times.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two water bottles were stored in cages on the bike's frame.  Two water bottles were stored in rear jersey pockets.  I bought a hydration backpack in KS once services started to get more spread out.  Some Western Express stretches require you to ride ~100 miles without a gas station.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of every day I "checked-in" with the SPOT personal locator beacon.  It has a tracking feature which I did not use in order to conserve battery life (the SPOT used AAA Lithium ion batteries which I didn't feel like tracking down during the trip).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Characteristic road dangers of each state&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed the route for the most part.  Particularly the western Virginia portion because it's composed of mostly quiet and extremely scenic country roads.  However, it would be incorrect to say that it's a safe trip because different regions presented unique challenges out on the road.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kentucky&lt;/strong&gt; - coal trucks, deep rumble strips + no shoulder, dogs  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missouri&lt;/strong&gt; - logging trucks, dogs  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kansas&lt;/strong&gt; - big rig trucks.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colorado&lt;/strong&gt; - lots of RVs, campers, and in general, drivers that seemed to pass very closely  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utah&lt;/strong&gt; - rental RV vehicles  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nevada&lt;/strong&gt; - deep rumble strips on highway 50, serious water challenges due to spread-out gas stations  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogs were a problem because folks out in the rural areas do not have fences.  I met a local cyclist out for a ride in Kentucky who had pepper spray mounted to his handlebars.  The only time I was truly concerned was when a pack of dogs from a neighborhood in Missouri surrounded me and I couldn't yell them off (they eventually went away).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semi-trailer_truck"&gt;Big rig trucks&lt;/a&gt; had to be treated with respect.  There were tons of Kentucky coal trucks hauling loads in the eastern portion.  I was repeatedly told that the logging trucks in Missouri were unable to stop going downhill due to the heavy loads.  On the two-lane highway 96 in Kansas, very large trucks would unavoidably pass closely and their size/speed would displace such a huge volume of air that I would get pulled towards the truck.  People have &lt;a href="http://www.pressherald.com/2013/06/27/crash-report-cites-truck-draft-in-trek-across-maine-cyclists-death/"&gt;died&lt;/a&gt; that way (getting sucked-in under the truck).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My strategy was to just pull over if a truck was approaching from behind and there was oncoming traffic that would prevent them from moving over.  Maybe typical touring cyclists with heavier loads (full camping gear, paniers) are more stable and do not have the air-driven "suck-in" problem?  I didn't mind pulling over: Besides the safety aspect, the drivers of these trucks had jobs to do and I was just on vacation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RVs were nerve-wracking because while a big-rig truck is (presumably) driven by a professional, RV owners are probably everyday people like you and me.  Especially the drivers of the rental RVs.  This knowledge made me very careful when an RV was about to pass.  Sometimes, I just pulled over.  Also, the folks in the western states take things to a new level!  In Colorado and westward, I saw &lt;a href="http://rv-roadtrips.thefuntimesguide.com/2010/02/rv_towing-2.php"&gt;triple towing&lt;/a&gt; for the first time (e.g., pickup truck towing a camper towing a boat).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Physical toll&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These things mainly happened because I wanted to do high mileage days without doing hardly any bike training before leaving.  The extra weight from gear made things worse than normal.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aching quadriceps in the second through third weeks from riding my way into shape.  They weren't sore, they just ached.  I had to easy-pedal in the small ring for a while, which was frustrating.  It was a really weird feeling but eventually went away.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Severe neck pain from constantly checking behind me for traffic because I was too dumb to take a mirror.  While this became somewhat manageable, it prevented me from doing more long distance rides after the trip.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numb big toes on each foot because my shoes fit poorly.  This persisted for a few months after the trip was over.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aching palms when leaning on handlebars because I did not wear gloves.  This persisted for far less time than the numb toes.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The neck pain was the worst and kept me from riding more once I was done.  It peaked in severity around the late second week and became manageable after the third week.  At its peak, the pain got to the point where I could no longer rotate my head and look behind me for traffic.  There are some simple solutions that I ignored:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ride less each day (no thanks).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ride more before leaving so that the neck muscles are more prepared (I went on about a half dozen rides to wake up the legs).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a touring bike or raise the stem to make the back more upright.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a simple handlebar mirror to avoid constantly turning around and looking for traffic.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Benefits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extreme patience with things like waiting in line, traffic, etc.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Newfound appreciation for remote areas of states that I was unlikely to ever visit.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to grind away in the big ring for 12+ hours and climb forever.  &lt;em&gt;Tradeoff:&lt;/em&gt; complete inability to sprint, which felt really weird.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What I would do differently&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a smaller tablet.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a handlebar mirror.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wear padded gloves.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend time finding better-fitting shoes.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to incorporate a &lt;a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/frame-bags/TangleFrameBag"&gt;frame bag&lt;/a&gt; so the saddle bag wouldn't be so large.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train more beforehand so that big days (~200 miles) could be done earlier in the trip.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out how to reliably inflate tires using a gas station air pump.  I imagine this is kinda tricky because it would be easy to overinflate.  I had trouble getting the frame pump to put out 110+ psi.  Low tire pressure on skinny road tires while carrying extra gear = a slow bike.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never turn down water in the desert (I did that once after miscalculating and really regretted it).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Images&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class="container" style="max-width:750px"&gt;

    &lt;ul class="gridderB"&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-1"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day01_IMGP0013.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-2"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day23_IMGP0093.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-3"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day02_IMGP0021.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-4"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day09_IMGP0148.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-5"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day14_IMGP0229.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-6"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day16_IMGP0241.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-7"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day16_IMGP0244.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-8"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day22_IMGP0085.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-9"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day29_IMGP0172.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-10"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day34_IMGP0244.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-11"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day07_IMGP0111.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-15"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day18_IMGP0024.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-12"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day11_IMGP0186.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-13"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day13_IMGP0198.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-14"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day19_IMGP0039.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-1" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day01_IMGP0013.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Some roads are in the middle of nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-2" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day23_IMGP0093.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Some roads are four lane highways.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-3" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day02_IMGP0021.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Drying washed clothes.  Since the flash was on, you can see the 3M reflective tape I added to the fenders.  It's difficult to see, but the small combination lock is wrapped around the head tube.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-4" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day09_IMGP0148.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Ohio River ferry crossing&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-5" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day14_IMGP0229.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Bridge under construction.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-6" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day16_IMGP0241.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;While everyone I met was using paper maps to navigate, I was using a GPS.  This was really nice and only failed me once.  I was riding along in Kansas and noticed traffic had pretty much disappeared.  In fact, the road became pretty desolate, but I kept going because the GPS said to.  Eventually, the road completely dead-ends into grass.  The Garmin mapping software was unaware a new road had been constructed off to the right.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-7" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day16_IMGP0244.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;One of the more obvious signs along the route.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-8" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day22_IMGP0085.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Eastern Colorado meets western Kansas.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-9" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day29_IMGP0172.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;I saw maybe five cars during the 5+ hours I was on this stretch in Utah.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-10" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day34_IMGP0244.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Nevada/Utah area.  I think everyone takes a picture like this.  One goes straight ahead for 20 miles, climbs a mountain, decends mountain, repeat ...  This is one of the longest stretches without services (about 80 miles).&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-11" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day07_IMGP0111.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;One runs into other cyclists riding the TransAmerica Trail.  I probably saw at least a dozen.  Everyone I met was camping.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-15" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day18_IMGP0024.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Self portrait.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-12" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day11_IMGP0186.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Road surfaces of the U.S., part I.  Different areas had different colors to the road, which I assume was indicative of whatever local quarry was used.  (Yes, things do get boring.)&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-13" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day13_IMGP0198.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Road surfaces of the U.S., part II.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-14" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-26-cycling-across-the-country/Day19_IMGP0039.JPG" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Road surfaces of the U.S., part III.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Anecdotes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was climbing a mountain pass in eastern Kentucky that wouldn't seem to end.  Eventually a driver pulled up in an old Camry to say hello.  After a brief exchange of formalities through the passenger side window, he says "hold on."  We proceed to continue making idle conversation as he pulls me up the mountain for about 5 minutes (I'm hanging onto the car while riding).  He was a super nice guy and even offered me a beer.  This was a narrow, winding road in Appalachia and I almost went off the edge when a car approached us from the opposite direction.  While I would have made it over the pass regardless, this kind gesture was an amazing psychological boost.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Ohio river is crossed at Cave-In-Rock, IL.  While there is no real story to go with this one, it was a unique experience to ride my bike onto a ferry, cross the river, and then ride off.  I guess it doesn't take much to entertain me.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crossing the Mississippi river at Chester, IL was nerve wracking.  There is a shoulder on the bridge but it's elevated by a foot so it's impossible to move over for traffic.  Vehicles are moving quickly and the Mississippi is a &lt;strong&gt;wide&lt;/strong&gt; river.  I asked a trooper if he had any crossing-by-bike advice, and he didn't.  All he said was, "maybe you'll get them to actually slow down," which wasn't exactly encouraging.  So I waited for a big gap and went all-out.  I don't know how, but I'd chosen perfectly since no traffic was in my lane.  I hadn't escaped the bridge for 30 seconds when big rigs come flying by.  It was one of the more stressful traffic situations of the trip.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm riding along in Missouri when all of a sudden I'm greeted with a "road closed" sign.  I mean, this is a pretty jarring experience because no other alternative really comes to mind.  I don't live here, I've never been here, and a detour would probably add 20 miles.  Instead of turning back (and taking what route?), I continue forward to see just how "closed" this road is.  Turns out, very closed.  See, the state of Missouri decided to spend money on rural bridges the summer I went on my trip.  In this case, the workers were replacing a bridge spanning a 30ft creek.  I dismount, walk over, and am eventually waived over this partially completed bridge.  This scenario repeated itself twice.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You see all kinds of nice and interesting people along the route.  I met a couple riding from California to Colorado to their own wedding.  One young guy had his dog with him on a trailer, but had to rent a car and take the dog home because of the heat.  Another rider was on a singlespeed bike.  Also, there's all kinds of other people just crossing the U.S. at any given time via other means.  Groups of touring motorcyclists are a common sight (I think they're as concerned/respectful of trucks and wind as cyclists).  Finally, there was one person I saw only briefly because I was descending fast.  I heard it was a visitor from Japan on some type of pedaling machine (I've already forgotten; a three wheeled cart maybe?) with a HUGE basket just filled with stuff.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I found it really hard to carry enough water in Nevada.  Unlike an east coast "hot," a Nevada hot doesn't drench your clothes in sweat.  Instead, you're constantly losing fluid while staying dry.  Well, one day I had miscalculated my fluid intake and was getting in serious trouble towards the end.  I was less than 15 miles from my destination but needed to make it up one final 20+ minute climb.  The problem was that I was developing a headache and pretty much out of water.  You can't just pull over at a gas station because this is rural Nevada -- there really aren't any outside of town.  So I'm climbing up the pass, deciding if I need to pull over and waive down a car, when I see an older gentleman already pulled over.  He's standing by his car, arm outstretched holding a water bottle, and shouting "domestique!"  This guy was scouting locations to do a bike trip with his own son and just happened to be there when I needed help the most.  It was incredible.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Days Inn in Montrose, Colorado had this laminated message on its beds.  One can find variations of this "Stranger within our gates" message in other places, but I had never seen it until then.  &lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this is a human institution to serve people, we hope that God will grant you peace and rest while you are under our roof.  May those that you love be near you in your thoughts and dreams.  Even though we may not get to know you, we hope that you will be comfortable and happy as if you were in your own house.  May the business that brought you our way prosper.  May every call you make and every message you receive add to your journey.  We are all travelers.  From "birth to death" we travel between eternities.  May these days be pleasant for you, profitable for society, helpful for those you meet, and a joy to those we know and love you best.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Closing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say that cycling across the U.S. is the safest thing in the world to do, but it certainly is one of the best ways to appreciate the landscape.  I went as fast as possible, but that made it fun for me.  Others may enjoy camping and spending time in the national parks along the route.  Regardless of how one approaches such a trip, he/she is unlikely to experience anything similar ever again.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Useful resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.adventurecycling.org"&gt;Adventure Cycling&lt;/a&gt; (maps, route information, forums)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/bicycletouring/"&gt;bicycletouring subreddit&lt;/a&gt; (riders post their travel logs here, which is super useful)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.crazyguyonabike.com/"&gt;crazyguyonabike&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
jQuery(document).ready(function ($) {

    // Call Gridder 1
    $(".gridderB").gridderExpander({
        scroll: true,
        scrollOffset: 60,
        scrollTo: "panel", // panel or listitem
        animationSpeed: 400,
        animationEasing: "easeInOutExpo",
        onStart: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Inititialized");
        },
        onContent: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Content Loaded");
            // $(".carousel").carousel();
        },
        onClosed: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Closed");
        }
    });

    // Call Gridder 1
    $(".gridderA").gridderExpander({
        scroll: true,
        scrollOffset: 60,
        scrollTo: "panel", // panel or listitem
        animationSpeed: 400,
        animationEasing: "easeInOutExpo",
        onStart: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Inititialized");
        },
        onContent: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Content Loaded");
            // $(".carousel").carousel();
        },
        onClosed: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Closed");
        }
    });

});
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="cycling"></category></entry><entry><title>Prindle 19 basics</title><link href="https://h-gens.github.io/prindle-19-basics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-23T21:12:00+01:00</updated><author><name>H.G.</name></author><id>tag:h-gens.github.io,2015-11-23:prindle-19-basics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a Prindle 19 catamaran as my first boat.  While I was comfortable on/in the water, I hardly knew anything about sailing.  There was a lot to learn, which is what this post attempts to document.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this will help someone else out there feel less intimidated with regards to getting into catamarans.  My advice is to ignore the racing-minded folk whose comments are always couched in terms of racing and remember one thing instead: &lt;em&gt;the basics of sailing are easy but sailing well is difficult&lt;/em&gt;.  Who cares about the latter if you just want to have fun.  Know your right-of-way rules and stay out of trouble.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="boat from stern" src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boat-from-stern.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Definitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bitter end&lt;/strong&gt; - The end of a line.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Block&lt;/strong&gt; - Nautical term for a pulley.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bolt rope&lt;/strong&gt; - The portion of the mainsail's luff that attaches to the mast.  It resembles a rope that has sailcloth wrapped around it.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bow&lt;/strong&gt; - Front of the boat.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clew&lt;/strong&gt; - The bottom corner of the sail that is closest to the stern.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curf&lt;/strong&gt; - The mast's channel through which the mainsail's bolt rope is fed.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foot&lt;/strong&gt; - The bottom of the sail.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forestay&lt;/strong&gt; - Metal cabling that extends from the bow to the top of the mast.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forestay Y&lt;/strong&gt; - The branching of the forestay into two cables terminating at the port/starboard bows.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Halyard&lt;/strong&gt; - A line that raises a sail.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Head&lt;/strong&gt;- The top of the sail.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luff&lt;/strong&gt; - The vertical edge of a raised sail that faces the bow.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mast locking hook&lt;/strong&gt; - Hook at the top of the mast where the main halyard ring attaches.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port&lt;/strong&gt; - Left side of the boat when standing in the middle of the boat and facing the bow.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safety position&lt;/strong&gt; - When the boat is positioned so that the wind is crossing its side with the jib/mainsheet lines let out so that the sails are not powered up.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shroud&lt;/strong&gt; - Metal cabling that extends from the top of the mast to either the port or starboard side of the boat.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stern&lt;/strong&gt; - Rear of the boat.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starboard&lt;/strong&gt; - Right side of the boat when standing in the middle of the boat and facing the bow.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parts_of_a_sail"&gt;Parts of a sail&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section I: Rigging&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise mast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert drain plugs.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert hull access port covers.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lock the rudders in the "up" position.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attach the tiller.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the boom to the mast and connect the mast rotation line from the boom, through the wishbone on the mast, and finally back through the V-cleat on the boom.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the traveler line, if necessary.  Thread the traveler line through the "eye strap" on the rear crossbar and tie a figure-8 knot at the bitter end.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the main blocks/sheet by shackling the base of the main blocks to the traveler.  Do not attach to the boom.  Consider tying together the bitter ends of the mainsheet and traveler line.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the beach wheels under the boat and parallel with the shrouds.  At each shroud, pull up tightly on the adjacent wheel's rope and wrap multiple times around the shroud.  Secure with an easy-to-remove knot (the multiple wraps will hold things in place).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move the boat so that its bows are facing into the wind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Raising the jib&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orient the S-hook on the jib halyard so that it appears as an "S" when viewed from the port side of the boat.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a shackle to connect the lower part of the S-hook to the eyelet on the jib's head.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partially zip the jib to the forestay by enclosing the forestay and jib halyard in the jib's luff.  (Once raised, the jib halyard should be total enclosed in the zipper just like the forestay.)  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise the jib.  Closer the zipper as it's raised.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the S-hook reaches the jib halyard ring near the top of the forestay, it must be locked into the halyard ring.  Pull on the jib halyard so that the S-hook goes through/above the halyard ring, and then pull down on the clew until the S-hook catches.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave around 1 foot of the jib's luff unzipped.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coil the remaining jib halyard line and store inside the zipper.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tightly wrap the jib downhaul around the forestay Y and secure in the jib cleat.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a bungee, furl the jib (wrap it around the forestay) to keep it from flapping.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Raising the main&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the main halyard's ring to the eyelet on the mainsail's head using a shackle.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feed the mainsail's bolt rope into the mast's curf.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise the mainsail by pulling on the main halyard.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mainsail is locked-in when the halyard ring reaches the mast’s locking hook.  The ring will fly completely past the hook if you pull up too hard on the main halyard.  If that happens, then the mainsail will lower without locking-in.  The idea is to pull up just hard enough so that the ring partially passes the locking hook.  If done correctly, the ring will then settle upon the hook when tension is removed from the main halyard.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tug down on the foot of the sail to ensure the halyard ring is locked.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coil the main halyard and store in a trampoline pocket.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thread the downhaul lines on each side of the mainsail.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a shackle to connect the boom to the clew of the mainsail.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave boom disconnected from the mainsheet blocks.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Launching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncleat jib/mainsail/traveler lines and let out plenty of line.  This will help avoid powering up the sails before launching.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roll the boat into the water.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Point the bow of the boat into the wind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have another person stand in the water at the bow while holding onto one side of the forestay Y.  This keeps the bows from rotating downwind and the sails from powering up.  One can think of this as "weather-vaning" the boat, and doing so effectively puts the boat into neutral.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove wheels and store on shore.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk the boat to deeper water and lock the rudders in the down position.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfurl the jib and connect the jib line to the clew.  This can be done with a knot, shackle, or climbing carabiner.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the mainsheet blocks to the boom using a shackle or carabiner.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give the bow a shove so that the boat rotates partially downwind into the safety position and hop on.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sheet in the jib, then the main.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rotate the centerboards to the down position if heading upwind.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;De-rigging and storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform the rigging steps in reverse.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suggestion:&lt;/em&gt; leave the drain plugs and hull access port covers open. Yes, water may go in the access port covers but it's going to drain/evaporate.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suggestion:&lt;/em&gt; place cushioning under the sterns.  Closed-cell foam works great.  Use kayak transportation foam (for car-topping) or cut a camping pad into sheets and stack them together.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the beach wheels' axle one foot forward of the front crossbar and secure the wheels' rope to shroud.  This keeps the boat at an angle and drains water.  The boat can also be left lying flat on the ground, which should be better for longer-term storage.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section II: Prindle 19 features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Barberhauler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is intended to help with downwind performance of the jib, I think.  The barberhauler line effectively pulls on the jib's clew so that the jib's foot is more parallel with the front crossbar.  I found it annoying since the previous owner had done a poor job of installing the small blocks that attach to the front crossbar.  I always meant to remove it but never got around to it.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Four-way jib system&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never figured out how to use this system properly and instead just set it in a constant configuration.  It's for people who actually know how to sail.  I would suggest removing it if you value trampoline space over performance.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rotating centerboards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are self-explanatory.  However, one does not rotate them all the way up when going downwind, which is when one makes use of a shock cord running from the shroud to the centerboard's pivoting cylinder.  From &lt;a href="http://www.catsailor.com/forums/ubbthreads.php?ubb=showflat&amp;amp;Number=52609"&gt;"gregP19" on catsailor.com&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Each centerboard had a short piece of pvc pipe that slips thru a hole in the board. This piece of pvc acts as a kind of axle allowing the board to pivot into or out of the trunk. The outboard end of this piece of pvc has a small hole that has a 3/8"(I think) piece of shock cord with a stopper knot to hold it in place. The other end of this piece of shock cord is formed into a loop. Hog rings work well here if they are taped to avoid scratching. This loop slides over the shroud chainplate with no slack. When you are going downwind you want your boards up, but not completely up into the trunk because the P19 doesn't have gaskets like the Tornado and you get gurgling in the trunk. The idea is to rotate the board up most of the way and lock it in place. To do this you push the piece of shock cord a couple of inches forward of the verticle slot in the trunk where it normally stays out of the way. You then push the centerboard up and rotate it forward until it jams against the shock cord and stays in place. It's a very simple, foolproof system."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section III: Righting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my brief experience, a capsize was always caused by a cleated mainsheet.  If the mainsheet is left uncleated at all times, the operator can quickly perform an emergency release during an unexpected gust.  Fortunately, the boat is not too difficult to right, especially with more than one person.  If all else fails, hail a motorboat and have them "walk the mast" with their hands while you lean backwards on the righting line.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To practice righting, intentionally capsize in deep-enough water by pulling on one of the shrouds or trapeze lines with a partner.  The boat will come down in slow motion if the mainsail is on.  Stay near the trampoline as the boat falls so that the boom does not hit you.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In high winds it can actually be easier to right the boat.  However, the boat must be positioned so that the wind flows under the mainsail (equivalent to the bows pointed into the wind).  I believe one would have to stand on the submerged hull closer to its bow in order to get the boat to rotate, although the Prindle 19 manual says to walk towards the stern.  I have no experience doing this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no experience righting from the turtle position (capsized boat with mast straight down in the water) because my mast was apparently well-sealed.  The idea is to take the righting line and lean backward from one of the hulls (same idea as righting from a non-turtled position).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dry-capsize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When on land, it is sometimes helpful to lay the boat on its side so that problems near the top of the mast can be sorted out.  Lay the boat down flat and clear our any rocks the hull might land on.  With another person (if necessary) grab a trapeze line and pull.  Once the boat reaches its tipping point, the mast can be caught by reaching for a shroud.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Righting procedure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uncleat the jib/mainsheets and traveler.  Let the lines out as far as possible.  If the lines are left cleated the sails may scoop up water and make righting impossible.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Throw the righting bag or line over the non-submerged hull.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand parallel with the front crossbar.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill the righting bag with water or attach righting line to harness hook by creating a loop in the line.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean back.  If present, the righting bag should be behind you and over one of your shoulders.  Your legs must be as far out as possible.  The idea is to push your center of mass away from the boat as far as possible in order to create a large righting moment.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The boat should right.  Be patient.  Watch out for the dolphin striker and hull falling down.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climb aboard.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the righting bag was used, it may begin to act like a huge sea anchor. Try to pull it aboard by pulling the bottom of the bag so that you don't have to fight the sea anchor effect.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section IV: Maintenance&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beach wheels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I purchased &lt;a href="http://www.murrays.com/mm5/merchant.mvc?Screen=PROD&amp;amp;Product_Code=13-1402&amp;amp;Category_Code=C-TP"&gt;beach wheels from murrays.com&lt;/a&gt; that are actually sourced from Florida Sailcraft.  I don’t think these require any maintenance and I’ve heard stories of beach wheels being left outside for years and years.  They're incredibly simple.  Each wheel’s bearings are actually just a bunch of nylon cylinders that are kept in place by a metal annulus on each side of the wheel (cotter pins keep each annulus in place).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Boat cover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sunbrella cover is suggested to preserve the trampoline from UV degradation.  I had one made locally.  The cheap/lazy solution is a tarp, which will only last about a season -- it's amazing what happens to a tarp left outside over a year.  It just starts to disintegrate, which doesn't sit well with me because that means the plastic material is dispersing into the environment.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bolt rope lubrication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apply paraffin wax to the mainsail's bolt rope to make raising/lowering easier.  "Gulf Wax Household Paraffin Wax" can be found at walmart or amazon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cleat rebuild&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As cleats age, they may need their Delrin bearings replaced.  This is an easy fix.  The cleats on my boat were Harken 150 types.  Order a Harken 150 rebuild kit and disassemble/clean cleat before replacing the bearings.  Some of my boat’s cleats were so old they did not use all the parts present in the rebuild kit.  Search for "H150 Cam Rebuild Kit" on &lt;a href="http://www.apsltd.com"&gt;ASP Ltd&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Non-skid decking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I placed spongy non-skid material on the hulls' top surfaces.  It was purchased from a company that sells a product called &lt;a href="http://www.raptordeck.com"&gt;"Raptor deck"&lt;/a&gt;.  They produce a foam non-skid with adhesive backing (grooves are cut into the foam surface to form diamond shapes).  They shape the panels according to a stencil or measurements you provide.  I had to sand off the previous non-skid that had been painted on so that the adhesive would adhere better.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Raising/lowering the mast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert the mast step hinge and the two mast hinge pins.  Have one person on the trampoline ready to support the mast and another person at the forestay.  The person at the forestay removes the forestay shackle and lets go of the forestay.  The person on the trampoline must support the mast and must be strong enough to do so.  Other people have devised electronic winching mechanisms so they can do this solo.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For transporting, the shrouds are coiled (without detaching them from the mast or the hulls' shroud chainplates) and secured to the trampoline.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wintering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove beach wheels from under the boat so that the hulls lay on the ground.  Optionally, place a strip of carpet under each hull.  Choose a width that prevents grass from growing into and possibly staining the hulls.  I've seen boats wintered without carpet and they seemed fine in the Spring.  Last I spoke with an older member of my sailing club, there are two schools of thought regarding the shrouds' tension (slackened or leave tightened) for mast-up boat storage over the winter.  From our discussion, the conclusion was to just leave them alone.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Replacement lines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of lines used on the Prindle 19 and their diameters.  Precut lines can be purchased from &lt;a href="http://www.saltydogmarine.com/product_info.php?cPath=421&amp;amp;products_id=3858"&gt;Salty Dog Marine&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td colspan=2&gt;Diameter&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td colspan=2&gt;Length&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Name&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;inches&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;mm&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;ft&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;cm&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;qty&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Barberhauler&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;487.7&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Batten ties&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/32&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1.83&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;55.9&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Downhaul&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;457.2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jib block adjustment&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;274.3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jib clew bridle&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;182.9&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jib halyard&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5/32&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;670.6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Jib sheet&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1005.8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Main halyard&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1859.3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Main sheet&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1219.2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Mast rotator&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;152.4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Rudder pull down&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;121.9&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Rudder pull up&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;152.4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Tramp lace&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;579.1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Trapeze adjustment&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1/4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;106.7&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Traveler&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5/16&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;304.8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Section V: Images&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class="container" style="max-width:750px"&gt;

    &lt;ul class="gridderA"&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-2"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-bolt.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-5"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/halyard-ring.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-6"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/wheels-to-shroud.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-8"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-clew-attach.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-7"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/hull-cushion.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-1"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/traveler-figure-8.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-3"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-mast-rotation.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-4"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/bowline-to-traveler.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-9"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/mast-step-hinge.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderA-content-10"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/mast-supporter.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-2" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-bolt.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Boom connects to mast with a single, long clevis pin.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-5" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/halyard-ring.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;This is an "Aussie" halyard ring because it has the halyard attachment ring offset ~30 degrees from center.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-6" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/wheels-to-shroud.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;When securing the beach wheels to the boat, wrap the shroud several times and secure in an easy-to-remove manner.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-8" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-clew-attach.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Example showing mainsheet blocks attached to the boom with a caribiner.  The shackle at the top connects the boom's outhaul with the mainsail's clew.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-7" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/hull-cushion.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Example of cushioning provided to the stern using stacked sheets of foam camping pads.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-1" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/traveler-figure-8.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Traveler line goes through a "pad eye" (or, "eye strap") on the rear cross bar and a figure-8 knot keeps it from being pulled through.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-3" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/boom-mast-rotation.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Mast rotation line.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-4" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/bowline-to-traveler.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Connect the traveler and mainsheet lines to make it easier to access the traveler line.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-9" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/mast-step-hinge.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Mast step hinge and pins.  I think that only one of the pins is truly a mast step hinge pin (the larger diameter one with the ring).&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderA-content-10" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/mast-supporter.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;PVC mast support for trailering.  The cutout on the left rests on the rear crossbar, and the cutout on the right supports the mast (place padding here).&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Coiling lines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use this technique when coiling lines to avoid twisting them and making the unraveling process a mess. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="container" style="max-width:750px"&gt;

    &lt;ul class="gridderB"&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-1"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-1.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-2"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-2.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-3"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-3.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-4"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-4.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-5"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-5.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-6"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-6.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li class="gridder-list" data-griddercontent="#gridderB-content-7"&gt;
            &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-7.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-1" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-1.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 1&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Alternately drape the line over each side of your hand.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-2" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-2.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 2&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Fold the draped line in half.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-3" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-3.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 3&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Use the remaining uncoiled line and wrap it around the folded line.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-4" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-4.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 4&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Take the remaining line and form a loop.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-5" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-5.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 5&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Push the loop through the inside center of the folded line.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-6" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-6.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 6&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Bring the loop back over the outside of the folded line.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt; 
    &lt;div id="gridderB-content-7" class="gridder-content"&gt;
        &lt;div class="row"&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;img src="images/2015-11-23-prindle19-howto/coiling-7.jpg" class="img-responsive" /&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class="col-sm-6"&gt;
                &lt;h2&gt;Step 7&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;p style="max-width:750px"&gt;Cinch tightly.  The bitter end should be secured and the coil now fixed in place.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Section VI: Helpful links&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thebeachcats.com"&gt;The Beach Cats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="docs/P19_18-2-1.pdf"&gt;Prindle 19 manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="docs/cat_trax.pdf"&gt;Cat trax instructions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
jQuery(document).ready(function ($) {

    // Call Gridder 1
    $(".gridderB").gridderExpander({
        scroll: true,
        scrollOffset: 60,
        scrollTo: "panel", // panel or listitem
        animationSpeed: 400,
        animationEasing: "easeInOutExpo",
        onStart: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Inititialized");
        },
        onContent: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Content Loaded");
            // $(".carousel").carousel();
        },
        onClosed: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Closed");
        }
    });

    // Call Gridder 1
    $(".gridderA").gridderExpander({
        scroll: true,
        scrollOffset: 60,
        scrollTo: "panel", // panel or listitem
        animationSpeed: 400,
        animationEasing: "easeInOutExpo",
        onStart: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Inititialized");
        },
        onContent: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Content Loaded");
            // $(".carousel").carousel();
        },
        onClosed: function(){
            // console.log("Gridder Closed");
        }
    });

});
&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="sailing"></category></entry></feed>